less than 24 hours ago a report was
released that will Echo around the world
it is 154 pages and I just finished
reading and digesting all of them yes
that includes the appendices and no I
didn't use gpt4 it revealed in a
nutshell that gpt4 shows Sparks of
artificial general intelligence the Holy
Grail of AI research and yes I was
skeptical then I read the paper I'm
going to break down only the most
important Revelations one by one first I
want to address the thought that you
must be having how could these guys have
discovered so much when the model has
only been out a week well first as they
lay out in the introduction they have
interacted with gpt4 during its early
development these researchers from
Microsoft have had the model for months
as early as October of last year or even
earlier they had the raw model the
unrestricted version not the final
version of gc4 that had been fine-tuned
to improve safety and reduce biases so
they had around six months to experiment
with the unrestrained gpt4 that's enough
build up it's time to get to the
revelations and all of them I'm going to
do in order aside from this one because
honestly it blew my mind on page 45 they
say gpt4 is able to use tools with very
minimal instruction and no
demonstrations and they make use of them
appropriately they go on to say that
this is an emergent capability and chat
gbt could not do this before I get into
the details I must remind myself that
one of the key moments in human
evolution was when we discovered how to
use tools so the fact that GT4 can use
them so well and chat TPT couldn't is
truly a milestone in Ai and human
history I'm going to show you more
examples throughout the video but let's
start with their examples it knows when
it needs to use a calculator and can use
it effectively in my path to AGI video I
talk about how it struggles with
characters and it knows how to call a
character API and work out the number of
characters now might not seem impressive
but that was one of its key weaknesses
before if that didn't impress you how
about text to image GT4 can output
detailed images based on a text prompt
these can then easily be rendered into
more detailed drawings using a model
like stable diffusion version 2.1 notice
how the model knew how to arrange the
objects based on the text prompt and at
this point I can't help but point out
that other companies like Adept AI are
training language models on tools such
as Photoshop the point is that once
language models understand how to use
tools effectively the sky is the limit
next the paper revealed that gpt4 passes
mock technical interviews on leak code
and they say that it could be
potentially hired right now as a
software engineer on page 21 it gives
the results of GPT 4's performance on
easy medium and hard leap code tasks and
it then somewhat modestly says it is
comparable to Human Performance well try
to remember these numbers like 86.4 for
the easy task and 14.3 the k equals 5
bit by the way is that they pick the
best of its five attempts deep in the
appendices you see this this is the
human level easy medium and hard by the
way they were a little bit generous with
humans because they didn't include those
guys who got none of the tasks right
they took those guys out of the database
and compared gpt4 only to those humans
that got at least one task right and you
thought it was just standard coding how
about 3D game development when given a
task to create a 3D game of some
complexity I must say the report says
that GT4 produces a working game in a
zero shot fashion chat GPT by contrast
responds that it can't do it when I say
a complex game the enemy is trying to
rush towards you and you have a Defender
that's trying to block the enemy it's
not a simple game as you can see from
this video they are not the only ones
who have used gpt4 to create a detailed
game and trust me I would talk about
this amazing achievement for longer but
I need to get on to the next topic and
that is that they tested Gypsy 4 on the
2022 International mathematics Olympiad
that was not in its database and trust
me I've studied for this kind of thing
and it is not easy it is an extremely
high level of math and as the authors
say solving this problem requires a more
creative approach as there is no clear
strategy for beginning the proof as you
might expect qc4 manages to produce a
correct proof as I have demonstrated in
other videos it does get some math
problems wrong as the paper points out
that's often due to technical
proficiency making basic calculation
errors but remember the paper proved
that it could use a calculator if given
access to one give GT4 tools and
honestly it is going to shock the world
next and this is a quick one but I loved
it give it firmi questions these are the
kind of questions asked in really
difficult interviews and they have no
easy answer things like how many golf
balls could you fit in a swimming pool
or please estimate roughly how many
Fermi questions are being asked every
day truly complex questions and Gypsy 4
can Hazard great guesses next and this
one was worth waiting for finally we get
a personal assistant that actually works
I know it's called Google Assistant but
it isn't really an assistant is it gpt4
can use available apis to retrieve
information about a user's calendar
coordinate with other people over email
book a dinner and message the user with
the details this is a sample of the
interactions it performed sending an
email to Luke and then receiving Luke's
reply checking the calendar then putting
the event in the calendar then sending
an email to Joe etc etc when this
becomes available in an app format we
will finally have that AI personal
assistant that we have been waiting for
moving on did you know that gpd4 can be
your personal handyman one of the
authors of the paper had a leak in their
bathroom they went through a diagnostic
process with Gypsy 4 and it figured out
what the problem was when the author
followed gpt4's advice what happened the
leak was gone the problem was solved and
if you thought that was impressive wait
till you see this if it's allowed to ask
enough questions as you can see about
gbc4 can build up a mental map of say a
house that is entering on the left you
can see a map of the true locations of
each room and on the right you can see
gpd4's mental image of them that was
revealed by the way by drawing a pie
plot this ability of course is going to
become very relevant when gpd4 gets
embodied and I'm going to talk about
that in my next video speaking of which
if you're learning anything from this
video please don't forget to leave a
like and let me know in the comments
next up is theory of mind and I have
done a whole video on this so do check
it out afterwards but essentially the
authors discovered the same thing that
we have which is to say that gpd4 can
build up a mental model of what other
people are thinking you can pause the
video and read the scenario yourself it
essentially involves knowing what Alice
must be thinking what she must believe
about a situation even though the
reality is different separating what is
actually true with what a human being
believes to be true this is a key
Milestone on the road to possible all
Consciousness but if you're interested
in that topic honestly check out my
video on it now I know at this point
you're thinking I must have covered the
best bits but no there's more on page 80
the authors sketch out how gpd4 is an
auto regressive model which means that
it bases its outputs on what has already
come before that's great but it stops it
from planning ahead it doesn't know how
its output is going to end before it
starts and I'm going to reveal the
implications of this fascinating
weakness in a couple of ways first with
their examples and then with one of my
own making in this task they try to get
gpt4 to create a poem which begins with
a sentence and then ends with the same
sentence in reverse order but it's Gotta
make sense gpt4 simply can't do it
because it doesn't know how its poem is
going to end before it starts remember
it's an auto regressive model after
repeatedly and unsuccessfully testing
Gypsy 4's ability to do this the authors
broke it down like this gpt4 is amazing
at incremental time ass but not as good
at discontinuous tasks incremental tasks
are those where you follow a standard
procedure building things up step by
step like composing a poem using a rhyme
scheme or writing a summary of a text
start at the beginning and then next
sentence Etc but discontinuous tasks
require you to know a bit about the
output the end result before you start
they give a great example of writing a
joke you kind of need to know the punch
line before you do the setup maybe
that's why Gypsy 4 is so bad at joke
telling it can't think of an amazing
punch line and then work backwards to
create the scenario around it I came up
with a simple demonstration of this to
show you guys try asking GPT for this
question how many words are in the full
response to this prompt if you think
about it it has to know the final result
of its output to give a correct answer
because it's just generating an answer
word by word token by token it can't do
this it said that there are 43 words in
the full response to this prompt
including the word in the question and
the answer okay that's kind of weird I
didn't want to include the question
itself but let's see if it got it right
I said list them out and count them and
then it went through including the
prompt which I didn't want but fine how
many words are in the full response etc
etc and lo and behold there were only 31
words in the prompt and the output but
remember it had said that there were 43
words it doesn't know the end result
when it starts before you conclude that
this will be a permanent block on
language models like 4 progressing
further Ponder this a paper came out in
January showing that it was at least
theoretically possible to augment large
language models with external memory and
the paper both asks and answers this
question such Works raise the question
of whether augmenting a language model
with an external feedback loop is merely
useful or fundamentally expands the
range of computations that can be
performed this paper gives an
affirmative answer now obviously it's
still a hugely leap from here to there
imagine if gpt4 gets access to an
external memory or say GT5 then as the
authors know you could have different
layers of language models one doing the
fast thinking subroutines and another
doing the slow thinking big picture
monitoring the output of the language
model and adjusting from there arguably
that would be the ultimate breakthrough
possibly even a dangerous breakthrough
speaking of dangerous on page 84 the
authors know that the unrestricted GT4
is incredible at propaganda and
conspiracy theories it can design entire
misinformation campaigns replete with
links and images and I worry that it's
only a matter of time before someone
jailbreaks this kind of version of gypsy
4 and uses it in the wild next and I
think this is quite a stunning admission
from researchers at Microsoft they say
that some people may ask for the ability
and right to decide and specify which
content they want or do not want to be
crawled they're flagging this up in
terms of privacy and potential lawsuits
the context they're giving is of models
like Gypsy 4 taking away jobs and if
they're taking away jobs from people
whose content has been crawled I
wouldn't be surprised if there's some
contention there two final points from
this bombshell paper the authors talk
about equipping llms large language
models with agency and intrinsic
motivation and say that this is a
fascinating and important direction for
future work this is in the context of
gypsy 4 not being motivated by anything
just being passive while I do think that
that's a fascinating direction for
future work but it's also a very
concerning one giving a language model
intrinsic motivation not only has
ethical concerns and questions like when
would it have rights then but it also
raises huge safety concerns of course
they do admit with this direction of
work great care would have to be taken
on alignment and safety I I'm not
personally too keen on this phrasing of
giving it motivation is a fascinating
and important direction as if it's
definitely something we should be
working on this is especially true in
the context of the final part of the
paper they admit that they don't really
know what is actually happening they
know what gpt4 is capable of but not
really why it's capable of those things
of course they propose hypotheses but
they end with this overall elucidating
the nature and mechanisms of AI systems
such as gpc4 is a formidable challenge
that has suddenly become important and
Urgent translated we need to figure out
how these things work and fast well I
definitely agree with that thank you so
much for watching to the end let me know
your thoughts in the comments and have a
wonderful day